Digital Tale of Genji - Feature Introduction.
デジタル源氏物語、機能紹介。
We will explain the Patapata Face Comparison.
パタパタ顔比較についてご説明します。
A tool to easily compare Genji Hyakunin Isshu editions that look identical at first glance.
一見同じに見える源氏百人一首を簡単に比較できるツールです。
For example, you can see the difference between closed eyes and open eyes.
例えば、目を閉じた「引目」と目を開いた「開目」の違いがわかります。
You can confirm differences in character faces using the image comparison tool.
人物の顔部分の違いを画像比較ツールで確認できます。
It uses vdiff.js.
vdiff.jsを利用しています。
Published by the ROIS-DS Center for Open Data in the Humanities.
ROIS-DS人文学オープンデータ共同利用センターが公開しています。
About the origin of the name "Patapata Face Comparison."
「パタパタ顔比較」の名称の由来です。
The motion resembles aori proofreading, where manuscripts are overlaid and flipped quickly.
原稿を重ね合わせて素早くめくるあおり校正に動きが似ています。
Please also refer to "About this page" for details.
詳細は「このページについて」もご参照ください。
Access it from the menu screen.
メニュー画面からアクセスします。
Select "Genji Hyakunin Isshu" under "Comparison of Illustration Images."
「挿絵画像の比較」から「源氏百人一首」を選択します。
Launch the image comparison tool.
画像比較ツールを起動します。
Click the "Compare (vdiff.js)" button.
「比較（vdiff.js）」ボタンをクリックします。
How to operate the image comparison tool.
画像比較ツールの操作方法です。
Move the dividing line left and right on the image.
画像上の分割線を左右に移動します。
You can dynamically confirm the differing parts of the two images.
2つの画像の異なる部分を動的に確認できます。
Move the dividing line to check the differences.
分割線を動かして違いを確認していきます。
Here is a comparison example.
比較事例をご紹介します。
Even back views that look identical have differences.
一見同一に見える後ろ姿でも違いがあります。
The two editions are displayed side by side.
2つの版を並べて比較します。
Using patapata reveals a very slight difference in part of the hair.
パタパタしてみると、髪の毛の一部にわずかな違いを発見できます。
Even the smallest differences can be confirmed.
ほんの小さな違いも確認できます。
Zoom in to examine the differences.
拡大して差異を確認します。
Here are some additional features.
その他の機能をご紹介します。
The highlight display feature.
強調表示機能です。
Only the differing parts of the two images are emphasized with highlighting.
2つの画像の異なる箇所だけハイライトで強調されます。
Noise from differences in photography conditions is mechanically removed.
撮影条件の違い等によるノイズは機械的に除去されます。
The red-blue display feature.
赤青表示機能です。
Differing parts of images are displayed in red and blue.
画像の異なる箇所が赤色・青色で表示されます。
Since noise removal is not performed, original differences can be confirmed.
ノイズ除去を行わないため、本来の差異を確認できます。
Digital Tale of Genji.
デジタル源氏物語。
Thank you for watching.
Digital Tale of Genji。